<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC7854 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7854.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC6396 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6396.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-rel SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-rel.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.petrie-grow-mrt-bmp SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.petrie-grow-mrt-bmp.xml">
	<!ENTITY IANA_PS_MSG_TYPE "TBD1">
	<!ENTITY IANA_PS_CODE_PEER_TLV "TBD2">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-lucente-grow-bmp-offline-01"
     ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     updates="7854">

    <front>
        <title>
	    BMP State Summaries
        </title>

        <author fullname="Paolo Lucente" initials="P" surname="Lucente">
            <organization>NTT</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Veemweg 23</street>
                    <city>Barneveld</city>
                    <code>3771</code>
                    <region>MT</region>
                    <country>NL</country>
                </postal>
                <email>paolo@ntt.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Camilo Cardona" initials="C" surname="Cardona">
            <organization>NTT</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>164-168, Carrer de Numancia</street>
                    <city>Barcelona</city>
                    <code>08029</code>
                    <country>Spain</country>
                </postal>
                <email>camilo@ntt.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Colin Petrie" initials="C." surname="Petrie">
            <organization>NTT</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Siriusdreef 70-72</street>
                    <city>Hoofddorp</city>
                    <code>2132 WT</code>
                    <country>NL</country>
                </postal>
                <email>colin@ntt.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Luuk Hendriks" initials="L." surname="Hendriks">
            <organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Science Park 400</street>
                    <city>Amsterdam</city>
                    <code>1098 XH</code>
                    <country>Netherlands</country>
                </postal>
                <email>luuk@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
            </address>
        </author>


        <date year="2025"/>

        <area>General</area>

        <workgroup>Global Routing Operations</workgroup>
        <keyword>BMP</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
		<xref target="RFC7854">BMP (BGP Monitoring Protocol)</xref> is perfectly
		suited for real-time consumption but less ideal in stream processing and
		off-wire historical scenario. The main issue is the dependence that parsing
		BGP Update PDUs has on knowing which capabilities have been agreed when
		establishing the BGP session with the peers, which could have happened long
		time ago (days, weeks, months).
	    </t>
        <t>
            This document introduces the concept of Summaries. It defines a new
            optional BMP message type, called State Summary, and a new TLV,
            called Summary Id.
            A Summary is similar to the initial synchronisation performed upon
            establishment of the BMP session: all BGP session information is
            exported in PeerUpNofication messages, and all RIB contents are
            exported in RouteMonitoring messages. All the messages carry the new
            Summary Id TLV, containing an ID uniquely identifying the summary
            these messages belong to. The messages are preceded by a State
            Summary message, carrying the same Summary Id TLV, as well as
            meta-data describing the Summary.
        </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="Introduction">
            <t>
		Correctly parsing BGP Update PDUs included in BMP messages (ie. Route
		Monitoring) does require a stateful approach by keeping track of
		capabilities exchanged at BGP Open time as reported by BMP Peer Up
		messages. 
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The role of Peer Up messages is solely BGP session event logging and
		the long-lived nature of sessions does pose the problem that a BGP
		Open message may have been received long time before parsing a BGP
		Update making challenging a stateful approach based on receipt of
		Peer Up.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">TLV support for BMP Route
		Monitoring and Peer Down Messages</xref> defines a Stateless Parsing
		TLV aimed at including relevant capabilities that have an impact in
		BGP Update message parsing as part of optional informational TLV in
		Route Monitoring messages. While the method is valid, in fact it does
		allow with minor effort to encapsulate BMP in MRT format for offline
		consumption as documented by <xref target="I-D.petrie-grow-mrt-bmp">
		Storing BMP messages in MRT Format</xref>, it comes with some drawbacks
		like extra verbosity and increased correlation effort at a BMP exporter,
		where resources may be limited.
	    </t>
        <t>
        Similar to how the necessary information carried in the BGP OPEN
        messages is sent from the exporter to the station only in the
        beginning of a BMP session (in forms of PeerUpNotifications), the
        contents of the RIBs is also only sent at the beginning (in forms of
        RouteMonitoring messages). In other words, to make correct and complete
        sense of offline BMP data, both current state (RIB contents) and session
        details (BGP OPEN Capabilities) to parse future state changes are
        required.
        </t>
	    <t>
            This document introduces Summaries, enabling synchronisation of both
            BGP session information and RIB contents anywhere in a BMP session.
            Summaries are enabled by the new optional State Summary message type
            and the new Summary Id TLV, both introduced in this document.
            A Summary is a collection of PeerUpNotification messages,
            RouteMonitoring messages and a single State Summary message, all
            carrying the newly introduced Summary Id TLV containing the unique
            identifier for that Summary. The State Summary message further
            contains TLVs with meta-data describing when the Summary was
            created, information on the exporting side such as sysName and IP
            address, information on the collecting side such as BMP station
            software name and versions, etc.
        </t>
        <t>
            The new concepts described in this document are not restricted to
            either the BMP exporter or the BMP station. By building upon TLVs,
            supported in all BMP message types from BMPv4, the Summary approach
            imposes minimal requirements over the initial synchronisation in BMP
            today. Furthermore, if at any point in the future another message
            type needs to be incorporated in a Summary, it will be a simple
            matter of attaching the Summary Id TLV to those messages.
            No existing message types have to be adapted to support Summaries.
        </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Terminology">
            <t>
		The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
		NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
		"MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
		described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>
		<xref target="RFC8174">RFC 8174</xref> when, and only when, they
		appear in all capitals, as shown here.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section
            title="State Summary message format"
            anchor="state-summary-message"
        >
            <t>
                The State Summary message starts with a BMP Common Header as
                defined in <xref target="RFC7854">Section 4.1 of</xref>.
                The Common Header is directly followed by non-indexed TLVs. The
                Summary Id TLV defined in
                <xref target="summary-id-tlv"/>
                MUST be present and SHOULD be the first of the TLVs. All other
                additional TLVs, listed in <xref target="meta-data-tlvs"/> are
                optional.
            </t>
            <t>
                The State Summary message can be generated by a BMP exporter or
                by a BMP station, as long as all required data for the
                PeerUpNotification and RouteMonitoring messages pertaining to
                the Summary are available. The State Summary message MUST be
                followed by those messages, with the Summary Id TLV attached.
            </t>
        <section title="Summary Information TLVs">
            <section title="Summary Id TLV" anchor="summary-id-tlv">
                <t>
                    The Summary Id TLV is the only mandatory TLV of a State
                    Summary message as defined in
                    <xref target="state-summary-message"/>.
                    It is a non-indexed TLV, following the standard structure as
                    defined in <xref target="TODO"/>, with a fixed value length
                    of 16 bytes. This allows the use of UUID version 4
                    identifiers, or provides sufficient space for alternative
                    schemes.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Optional meta-data TLVs" anchor="meta-data-tlvs">
        <t>
        The Peer Summary message SHOULD carry TLVs providing additional
        information on the BMP session being summarized. These Summary
        Information TLVs describe the BMP exporter and station involved,
        and the date and time the summary was generated.
        By embedding these TLVs in the offline file, a consumer of the
        file does not have to rely on the filename or other external
        data to get these
        types of information.

        All TLVs are non-indexed. 

        <list style="symbols">
        <t>
            Type = TBD3: Datetime of summary
            <list style="empty">
            <t>
                Length: 8 bytes
            </t>
            <t>
                Value: 64bit UNIX epoch, in seconds
            </t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>
            Type = TBD4: Exporter IP address
            <list style="empty">
            <t>
                Length: 16 bytes
            </t>
            <t>
                Value: IPv6 or IPv4-mapped IPv6 address
            </t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>
            Type = TBD5: Exporter sysName
            <list style="empty">
            <t>
                Length: variable, non-zero, describing the number of bytes
            </t>
            <t>
                Value: UTF-8 string
            </t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>
            Type = TBD6: Exporter sysDesc
            <list style="empty">
            <t>
                Length: variable, non-zero, describing the number of bytes
            </t>
            <t>
                Value: UTF-8 string
            </t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>
            Type = TBD7: Station IP address
            <list style="empty">
            <t>
                Length: variable, non-zero, describing the number of bytes
            </t>
            <t>
                Value: IPv6 or IPv4-mapped IPv6 address
            </t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>
            Type = TBD8: Station sysName
            <list style="empty">
            <t>
                Length: variable, non-zero, describing the number of bytes
            </t>
            <t>
                Value: UTF-8 string
            </t>
            </list>
        </t>
        <t>
            Type = TBD9: Station sysDesc
            <list style="empty">
            <t>
                Length: variable, non-zero, describing the number of bytes
            </t>
            <t>
                Value: UTF-8 string
            </t>
            </list>
        </t>

        </list>


            </t>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section title="Summary/synthetic flag">
    <t>
        Within the Peer flags field in the Per-Peer Header, as defined in
        <xref target="RFC7854">Section 4.2 of</xref>, this document defines bit 4
        as the 'S' bit, indicating the message is part of a summary. Note that
        contextual information from a Peer Summary message is required to
        determine whether a message with the 'S' bit set to 1 is generated by
        the exporter or by the BMP station.
            <figure anchor="BMP-Peer-Summary-flag" align="center"
                title="Summary flag"
            >
                <artwork align="center">
                    <![CDATA[
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 |V|L|A|O|S| Rsv |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                        ]]>
                </artwork>
            </figure>
    </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Third party off-wire encoding formats">
            <t>
		While this document does define a way to facilitate stream processing,
		replay and, more in general, consumption of raw BMP data offline,
		similar benefits may be harnessed by third party off-wire formats in
		which BMP can be encapsulated into, for example MRT (Multi-Threaded
		Routing Toolkit) as defined by <xref target="RFC6396">RFC 6396</xref>.
		As a result of that, this document does not recommend a preferred way
		to stream process or store BMP data offline. 
            </t>
        </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Operational Considerations" anchor="opcon">
        <section title="Exporter vs. Station">
            <t>
                TODO 
            </t>
            <section title="Exporter use-cases / benefits">
            <t>
                TODO 
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Station use-cases / benefits">
            <t>
		The Peer Summary message injection in a BMP feed is done by an online
		BMP station for consumption by an offline consumer. The advantage of
		creating summaries at the online BMP station (for example, as opposed
		to creating them at a BMP exporter) is that it has awareness of how
		offline data is being organized, for example:
	    <list style="symbols">
		<t>
		    If BMP data is saved in files and a new file is created every five
		    minutes, it may make sense to include the summary at the beginning
		    of each file; or 
		</t>
		<t>
		    If BMP data is streamed onto a message bus like Kafka that supports
		    partitioning, it may be needed to broadcast summaries over each of
		    the partitions as they may be attended by different consumers.
		</t>
	    </list>
            </t>
	    <t>
		A BMP station receiving multiple Peer Up for the same peer should
		perform state compression and include in the Peer Summary the last
		one received, based on timestamp, at the time the summary is being
		generated. In other words, the summary is not meant, for example if
		a BGP session is flapping, as event reporting and this is left to
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-rel">BMP Route Event Logging</xref>.
	    </t>
        </section>
        </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
		It is not believed that this document adds any additional security
		considerations.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
		IANA is asked to allocate a new Peer Summary message type in the BMP
		Message Types registry with value &IANA_PS_MSG_TYPE;. IANA is also
		asked to to create a registry within the BMP group, named "BMP Peer
		Summary Message TLVs".
	    </t>
	    <t>
		Registration procedures for this registry are:
	    </t>
<texttable>
        <ttcol align='center'>Range</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>Registration Procedures</ttcol>

        <c>0-32767</c>
        <c>Standards Action</c>
        <c>32768-65530</c>
        <c>First Come, First Served</c>
        <c>65531-65534</c>
        <c>Experimental</c>
        <c>65535</c>
        <c>Reserved</c>
</texttable>
	    <t>
		Initial values for this registry are:
	    </t>
<texttable>
        <ttcol align='center'>Type</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>Description</ttcol>
        <ttcol align='center'>Reference</ttcol>

        <c>&IANA_PS_CODE_PEER_TLV;</c>
        <c>Peer</c>
        <c>this document</c> 
</texttable>
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title="Normative References">
		&RFC2119;
		&RFC8174;

		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7854.xml"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6396.xml"?>

		&I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv;
		&I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-rel;
		&I-D.petrie-grow-mrt-bmp;
        </references>

        <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
            <t>
		TBD
            </t>
        </section>

    </back>
</rfc>
